Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection
1954-2014
1980-2010
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bravo, Estela
Bravo, Ernesto
TAM.616
79.5 Linear Feet in 71 record cartons and 17 media boxes.
1365 videocassettes on Umatic and Betacam.
56 film reels
68.3 Gigabytes in 82 digital video files and on 16 DVDs.
Estela Bravo (1933- ) is an American-born documentary filmmaker who has been creating films on Cuba and Latin America with her husband Ernesto Bravo since the 1980s. Estela and Ernesto Bravo moved to Cuba in the early 1960s, and as a result many of Estela's films focus on political and cultural relations between the United States and Cuba. The collection contains over 1,300 video tapes and film reels recorded by Bravo throughout her career. In addition to full-length features and video footage, the collection contains a small amount of ephemera, correspondence, home movies, and documentation related to the promotion and licensing of Bravo's films. Footage in this collection consists of interviews with political leaders and celebrities; scenes of historical events, marches, demonstrations, and performances; battle footage; clips from Cuba's State Council archives; speeches by Fidel Castro, Nelson Mandela, and others; and background footage (b-roll) used in finished films. This footage is primarily recorded on U-matic and Betacam video tapes, and produced on film reels, VHS, and DVD for screening and distribution. This collection has been partially digitized, and only the digitized footage is currently accessible to researchers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Estela and Ernesto Bravo in 2012; additional materials were donated by the Bravos in 2013, 2015, 2015, and 2017, and by Angela Carrenno in 2015.
Appraisal
Twelve tapes were damaged beyond repair and removed from the collection. Duplicate recordings of completed documentaries on VHS, Betacam and digital formats were also removed from the collection. Additionally, a small number of electronic files that were not created by Estela or Ernesto Bravo were deemed out of scope and deaccessioned.
In June 2021, ten boxes containing 164 digitized tapes contaminated by mold were photographed by Media Preservation Unit staff and deaccessioned.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into 32 series by documentary film or by record type. The first 28 series are arranged in alphabetical order by film title. Within each series, materials are grouped by genre. Completed documentaries and edited fragments of documentaries are listed at the beginning of each series. They are followed by interview footage, transcripts, and other papers related to coordinating interviews. These materials are listed in alphabetical order by interviewee last name. Interviews are followed by general footage, film clips, and papers. In some cases, footage is listed in alphabetical order by title, but many of these clips have not been fully arranged.
Series XXIX: Independent and Unidentified Footage, 1980-1994 contains interviews and footage that is not associated with a specific documentary feature or cannot be identified with a completed film. This footage is not grouped by genre, and is arranged in alphabetical order by title or interviewee last name.
Materials in Series XXX: Collected Ephemera and Publications are arranged alphabetically by title or by general topic. Additional films related to Estela and Ernesto Bravo's personal lives are arranged in Series XXXI: Estela and Ernesto Bravo Family Films. Several of these films were originally numbered by the donors. Numbered items are listed in sequential order, while films that were not numbered are listed in alphabetical order by title.
Series XXXII: Gema de Cuba, Estela and Ernesto Bravo's most recent documentary, was added to the collection in 2017 and has not been incorporated into the existing arrangement.
Biographical Note
Estela Bravo (1933- ) is an American-born documentary filmmaker who has been creating films on Cuba and Latin America with her husband Ernesto Bravo since the 1980s. The Bravos moved to Cuba in the early 1960s, and as a result many of Estela Bravo's films focus on political and cultural relations between the United States and Cuba. Bravo's documentaries have aired on television networks including PBS (US), CBC (Canada), Channel 4 (UK) Canal Plus (France), and at international film festivals and retrospectives honoring her work.
Estela Bravo was born on June 8, 1933 in Brooklyn, New York. The youngest of three daughters, she was raised in a family of working-class European immigrants. Estela worked for the Furriers Union while studying sociology at night at Brooklyn College. In 1953 she helped organize a group called Students for a Peaceful World. She attended the 3rd World Student Congress in Warsaw, Poland as a representative for the Students for a Peaceful World, where she met Ernesto Bravo.
Ernesto Mario Bravo (1929- ) was born in Argentina on April 7, 1929. Bravo studied medicine at the University of Buenos Aires. In 1951, while still a student, he was targeted by the state police for his participation in a student strike and tried on charges of organizing anti-government student activities.
Estela and Ernesto Bravo married in January of 1956. They moved to Cuba in 1963 after Ernesto was offered a position as a Professor of Biochemistry at the Medical School of the University of Havana. In Cuba, Estela Bravo worked at the cultural institution Casa de las Américas where she organized programs promoting folk and protest music. She later began developing television programs and creating short documentaries based on archival footage, which documented notable figures like the Rosenbergs, Malcolm X, and Paul Robeson. Ernesto wrote many of the scripts for these short films. Estela Bravo completed her first full-length documentary in 1980, Those Who Left, which told the story of Cubans who left the island after the 1959 revolution. In addition to his teaching career, Ernesto Bravo has worked collaborator with his wife on her many documentary films, and has written a number of books, including Modern Medicine in Cuba (1995) and Development within Underdevelopment: New Trends in Cuban Medicine (1998).
As of 2016, Estela and Ernesto Bravo continue to make films. In 2014, they were honored in South Africa by the Mandela Foundation, they released films about Gabriel García Márquez and Commander Juan Almeida, and they updated their 2007 film, Who am I? The Found Children of Argentina.
Filmography
1980 Those Who Left
1982 Cubans in Peru
1982 A Beautiful Mission
1983 The Marielitos
1984 Silvio and Pablo in Argentina
1984 Maurice Bishop
1984 The National Ballet of Cuba in Argentina
1984 The National Ballet of Cuba in Peru
1985 The Missing Children
1985 Children in Debt
1985 The Hour of the People
1986 Returning to Chile
1987 Who's Running the Show
1987 Holy Father and Gloria
1989 Americans in Cuba
1990 Cuba/South Africa: After the Battle
1990 Flotilla to Cuba
1990 Namibia: The Last Colony
1991 Mandela Visits Jamaica
1991 Mandela in Cuba
1992 Miami-Havana
1992 The Three Rafters
1993 The Cuban Excludables
1998 From Miami to Washington
2000 Fidel: The Untold Story
2000 Camp Kinderland in Havana
2004 Free to Fly
2007 "Who am I?" The Found Children of Argentina
2010 Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba
2011 Anecdotes about Fidel
2012 Roberto To Love and Fight for Life
2013 Mandela and Fidel
2014 A Conversation with García Márquez about his Friend Fidel
2014 A Conversation with Commander Juan Almeida
2014 "Who am I?" The Found Children of Argentina (Update)
Scope and Content Note
The Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection (dates 1959-2014) contains interviews, footage, and full-length films from documentaries created by filmmaker Estela Bravo between the 1980s and early 2000s. The collection contains over 1,300 video tapes and film reels recorded by Bravo throughout her career. In addition to full-length documentaries and video footage, the collection also contains a small amount of ephemera, correspondence, and documentation related to the promotion and licensing of Bravo's films. Footage in this collection consists of interviews with political leaders and celebrities; scenes of important events, marches, demonstrations, and performances; battle footage; historical clips from Cuba's State Council archives; speeches by Fidel Castro, Nelson Mandela, and others; and background footage (b-roll) used in finished films. This footage was primarily recorded on U-matic and Betacam video tapes, and produced on film reels, VHS, and DVD for screening and distribution.
Many of Bravo's films focus broadly on Cuba after the revolution and its relationship with the United States and other countries. Bravo's films address other issues related to Latin American politics and culture, exploring topics such as: children abducted during Argentina's "Dirty War;" Chile under the Pinochet dictatorship; the assassination of Maurice Bishop in Grenada; social and economic problems caused by Latin American debts owed to the United States; struggles to end apartheid in South Africa; and a 1984 concert featuring Cuban musicians Silvio Rodriguez and Pablo Milanes in Buenos Aires.
The most extensive footage comes from Fidel: The Untold Story and its follow-up Anecdotes about Fidel. There are more than 400 video recordings related to these films. Among the highlights of this material are interviews with notable individuals including: Arthur Schlesinger, Ramsey Clark, George McGovern, Alice Walker, Harry Belafonte, Philip Agee, Ted Turner, Edward Heath, Jorge Risquet, Ricardo Alarcón, Vilma Espín, and Angela Davis. These videos also contain interviews with supporters of the anti-Castro movement including counter-revolutionaries like Orlando Bosch.
Other films featured prominently in this collection address the social consequences of tensions between the United States and Cuba. These films include Americans in Cuba, documenting American who moved to Cuba after the revolution; The Cuban Excludables, which follows Cubans who came to the United States during the Mariel boatlift and the conditions they faced while being detained by US authorities; and Miami-Havana, a film that explores the consequences of travel and communication restrictions between Cuba and the United States.
Not all of Bravo's films are represented in the collection. Footage from some films may be more complete than others, while footage from other films does not appear in the collection at all. In other cases video footage is duplicated in multiple series. Bravo frequently reused older footage in follow-up documentaries to provide background and context for a subsequent film. For example, footage from the 1985 film, Missing Children, also appears in the 2007 documentary, Who Am I?: The Found Children of Argentina. Additionally, there are many interviews that exceed the duration of a single tape, and are recorded on multiple tapes. These interviews will contain pauses and breaks in the conversation to allow the videographer to change tapes.
The collection also contains footage that was not included in any feature film. These recordings may have been shot with a potential film in mind, but were never included in any completed feature. The Bravos also recorded special events or interviews with notable individuals, even though they did not intend to include them in a specific documentary. These recordings include an interview with Mikis Theodrakis, a Greek songwriter/composer and supporter of Fidel Castro, and an interview with Brazilian Communist Party leader Luis Carlos Prestes (1898-1990). There is also some footage which is unidentified or has not yet been associated with a specific feature film.
Between 2014 and 2015, two additional donations of periodicals, programs, playbills, transcripts, and related items were added to the collection. They may be found in Series XXX: Ephemera and Publications. Transcripts and partial transcripts from this donation relate to the film Fidel: The Untold Story and have been added to Series VIII. Transcripts contain interviews of some individuals for which there is no film footage, including Walter Sisulu and Kalema Moutante. A small set of film reels, donated in 2014, contain personal family footage of Estela and Ernesto Bravo with friends and family members, most of which were filmed in 1958. These reels are arranged in Series XXXI: Estela and Ernesto Bravo Family Films.
Many of the dates in this collection have been estimated based on the content and release date of the film. Specific dates are listed if they appeared on the cassette annotations, while others were inferred from the film's content. The word "Bump" appears in several titles, and was used by Estela Bravo to indicate clips selected from a previous, longer, piece of footage.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Commercial copies of Estela Bravo's documentaries have been transferred to the Avery Fisher Center in Bobst Library. Additionally, copies of the following serials were transferred to Tamiment's library collections: Bohemi, Cine Cubano, Cuba Magazine, Cuba Update, Cuba International, Education, Joven Cuba, OCLAE, Prisma, Science Magazine, The Sciences. Please check the library catalog for holdings.
United States -- Foreign Relations -- Cuba.; Cuba -- Foreign Relations -- United States.; Chile.; Food relief, American -- Cuba.; Argentina.; Uruguay -- Politics and government -- 1973-1985.; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1973-1988.; Jamaica.; Cuban Americans -- Florida -- Miami -- Family relationships.; Angola -- History -- Civil War, 1975-2002 -- Participation, Cuban.; Bolivia.; Disappeared persons -- Argentina.; Namibia.; Human rights -- Argentina.; Documentary films; Angola -- History -- South African Incursions, 1978-1990.; Cuba.; Detentions of persons -- United States.; Cuba -- Social conditions.; Mariel Boatlift, 1980.; Debts, External -- South America.; Grenada -- Politics and government -- 1974.; Cuba -- History -- 20th century.; Argentina -- History -- Dirty War, 1976-1983.; Alonso, Alicia, 1921- -- Interviews; Asociación de Abuelas de Plaza de Mayo; Mandela, Nelson, 1918-2013; Núñez Jiménez, Antonio -- Interviews; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007 -- Interviews; González, Elián, 1993-; Bussi de Allende, Hortensia -- Interviews; Walker, Alice, 1944- -- Interviews; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944- -- Interviews; Ballet Nacional de Cuba; Almeida, Juan -- Interviews; García Márquez, Gabriel, 1927-2014 -- Interviews; Agee, Philip. -- Interviews; Pollack, Sydney, 1934-2008 -- Interviews; Frady, Marshall -- Interviews; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012 -- Interviews; Rabinowitz, Victor -- Interviews; Castro, Raúl, 1930- -- Interviews; Bishop, Maurice; John Paul II, Pope, 1920-2005
- Series I: Americans in Cuba, Those Who Came, 1988-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  In the 1989 film Americans in Cuba, Estela Bravo tells the stories of several Americans who stayed in Cuba after the 1959 revolution. Some of the Americans featured in the documentary lived in Cuba prior and decided to remain after the new government was established, while others decided to immigrate to Cuba in the period following the revolution. This series contains footage from the 43-minute film, including interviews with women such as Elfriede Mahler; Marjorie Moore; Lorna Burdsall; Lois Kroehler, a missionary, music teacher and peace advocate who came to Cuba in 1949; Jean McEvoy and Ellen Rosensweig, who is interviewed with her husband and children and comments on the differences between her life in Cuba and her visits to see her family in California. Footage from this film contains one-on-one interviews, performances, discussions in the street or in other venues, and scenes of the various locations where the women live.
  - "Americans who stayed in Cuba", circa 1989; cuid17594 (Box 1, Cassette ref8)
  - Black, Helen: Interview, circa 1988; cuid17595 (Box 79, Dvd ref317)
    This interview contains footage from religious summer camp in Placetas, Cuba. It features Helen Black, an American living in Cuba for many years, who works at the camp.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:52:27.
  - Black, Helen: Summer Camp Footage, 1988 August 24; cuid17596 (Box 98, Dvd ref1074)
    Scope and Contents
    This video features footage of Helen Black's religious summer camp in Cuba. It begins with footage of a music lesson in the camp's chapel, and then shows campers playing volleyball on a large lawn. The video also shows Helen Black and Estela Bravo walking to a pond where several of the campers are swimming. Bravo and Black talk informally about the camp property and briefly about Elfriede Mahler, who Bravo also featured in her documentary Americans in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:35.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, 1988 August 25; cuid17597 (Box 97, Dvd ref285)
    This video features an interview with Helen Black. She begins by discussing the religious summer camps she runs in Cuba, and notes that the camps have not had any problems operating under Cuban government rules. She discusses her identity as an American in Cuba, traveling to Cuba for the first time in 1948, and her decision to stay after the revolution. She describes some of the changes she saw in Cuba after the revolution, and talks generally about how religious people and religion is treated in the country.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:42.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, circa 1988; cuid17598 (Box 14, Cassette ref309)
    This video contains footage of a party held for Helen's 40th anniversary at the church summer camp. She is opening presents and talking with party guests. The other half of this video contains footage from an interview with Helen Black about religion, particularly Protestantism, in Cuba, and the government's attitude toward the church.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:15:08.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, circa 1988; cuid17599 (Box 14, Cassette ref310)
    This video begins with footage of the grounds and people at a religious summer camp in Cuba. The video mostly contains footage from an interview with Helen Black: she talks about coming to Cuba in 1948 as a missionary, her religious work in Cuba, and how religious people and religion are treated in the country.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:14.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, circa 1988; cuid17600 (Box 14, Cassette ref325)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:20:39.
    This video begins with brief interviews of teachers at a campfire meeting at Helen Black's Christian youth camp in Cuba. The meeting is also a birthday party for Helen where people are eating cake and singing. The video ends with a church service at the camp with people singing and eating.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, circa 1988; cuid17601 (Box 14, Cassette ref327)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:19:28.
    This video contains background, interior, and exterior footage of a Christian camp in Cuba. Most of the footage is filmed while the camp participants are having dinner. There is an interview with Helen Black discussing the history of the camp. The backgroud conversations, songs, and prayers during the meal are in Spanish.
  - Black, Helen: Interview, 1988 August 25; cuid17602 (Box 98, Dvd ref1083)
    This interview with Helen Black begins with a discussion about her work in religious summer camps and her first travels to Cuba in 1951. She describes the types of people who came to her camps and the effect of the revolution on the religious community in which she lived. She explains that her camps were allowed to operate much like they did before the revolution, although government required the camps seek permission to operate. She discusses her family in the United States and the difficulties of traveling between the two countries. She also talks about what she sees as the positive and negative changes in Cuba since the revolution. At the end of the video she shares her personal philosophy in both English and Spanish, and explains that her biggest desire in life is to do God's will and help others embrace his message.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:08.
  - Burdsall, Lorna: Interview, 1988 May 17; cuid17603 (Box 98, Dvd ref1082)
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Lorna Burdsall (1928-2010) moved to Cuba in 1955 with her husband, who fought with Fidel Castro in the Cuban revolution. She was a dancer who trained with Martha Graham and studied at the Julliard School. In 1953 she met a young Cuban, Manuel Pineiro, who was studying business administration at Columbia. They married in New York but he left for Cuba to join Castro's forces shortly after their wedding. She joined him in 1955 and lived in Cuba for the rest of her life. Burdsall taught at the National Dance School and was a founding member of Conjunto Nacional de Danza Moderna, which she eventually directed. Burdsall was with the company for nearly 20 years and created numerous works reflecting the spirit of the Cuban people. In 1977 she became the national director of dance and modern dance advisor to the Minister of Culture.
    This interview with Lorna Burdsall begins with a discussion about her background as a dancer and the events that brought her to Cuba. She explains that she met her husband who was Cuban in 1953, and moved to Cuba with him in 1955. She discusses her love of modern dance, and describes joining the Department of Modern Dance in Cuba's National Theater in the early 1960s. She talks about her dance career in Cuba and the country has shaped her life. She discusses her experience performing, training and recruiting dancers, and the subsidies the government provides to the arts. She also discusses traveling between the US and Cuba, and some of the problems the country faces because of its poor relationship with the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:17.
  - Burdsall, Lorna: Dance Class "Cassette #13", 1988 May 18; cuid17605 (Box 97, Dvd ref270)
    This video begins with footage of Lorna Brudsall's dance class. At minute 9:30 the footage features a group interview with class members and Burdsall. Members of the class discuss what they like about the class, their personal backgrounds, their jobs outside of the class, and the reasons they were attracted to taking dance classes with Burdsall.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:18:23.
  - Burdsall, Lorna: Dance Class "Cassette #14", 1988 May 18; cuid17606 (Box 97, Dvd ref273)
    This video features footage from a dance class led by Lorna Burdsall.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:11:25.
  - Burdsall, Burdsall / Paskalitis, Barbara: Interview Segments, circa 1988; cuid17638 (Box 98, Dvd ref1090)